Howard Baetzhold Papers, 1952-2012
Elmira College
Howard Baetzhold Papers, 1952-2012
The Howard Baetzhold Papers contain materials from Baetzhold’s tenure at the Mark Twain Papers at the University of California and correspondence with other members of the Twain scholarly community. The correspondence contains little in the way of scholarship and primarily focuses on Baetzhold’s professional and personal relationships in Mark Twain studies.
.83 linear ft.
Baetzhold, Howard G., 1923-
Mark Twain Archive, Gannett-Tripp Library, Elmira College, Elmira, N.Y.
One restricted document in Container 2 folder 4 [restricted until 2035]
“[Howard Baetzhold] was born January 1, 1923 in Buffalo, New York to Howard K. and Harriet H. Baetzhold.
After graduating from Brown University and serving in the U.S. Air Force in World War II, Howard returned to Brown where he met his wife, Nancy M. Cheesman, and soon after began their loving and supportive 60-year marriage. They moved to Madison Wisconsin, where Howard earned his PhD at the University of Wisconsin Madison.
Indianapolis became their home in 1953 when Howard accepted a position in the Butler University English Department and began his tenured academic career. From 1981 to 1985 Howard served as head of the English Department and was named the Rebecca Clifton Reade Professor of English Emeritus. He retired from Butler University in 1988.
Howard was a nationally recognized Mark Twain scholar, writing and editing publications for over 40 years. He authored Mark Twain and John Bull: The British Connection (Indiana, 1970) and co-authored The Bible According to Mark Twain: Writing of Heaven, Eden and the Flood (University of Georgia Press, 1995). He was a generous supporter and advisor to the Center for Mark Twain Studies at Elmira College. Howard shared his expertise with the University of California's Mark Twain Papers and Project where he was one of the original editors of the Works of Mark Twain. He was one of the world's true experts on the contents of the archive of Mark Twain's papers at Berkeley. In 2001 at The Fourth International Conference on the State of Mark Twain Studies, Howard received the Henry Nash Smith Award recognizing his lasting contributions to Mark Twain Studies.
During his whole life, Howard fostered a love of water and was a competitive swimmer in high school and college. He was a member of the British Sub-Aqua Club of Indiana and for a time, taught scuba diving at the Jordan YMCA. Howard continued swimming through the U.S. Masters Swimming Program well into his 70's"
Howard Baetzhold died on July 7, 2012.
Bancroft Library. Mark Twain Project; Baetzhold, Howard G., 1923-; Hirst, Robert H.
The Howard Baetzhold papers are comprised of correspondence, NEH grant materials and materials concerning the Mark Twain Papers at the Bancroft Library, University of California. The materials related to the Mark Twain Papers where Howard Baetzhold was a contributor and writer is the area most concentrated on Baetzhold’s scholarly activities in the field of Mark Twain studies.
The collection contains little evidence of Baetzhold’s academic contributions or research areas in the field of Mark Twain studies.
- Series 1: Howard Baetzhold Papers, 1952 - 2012; The collection is organized alphabetically by correspondent last name with a miscellaneous correspondence file at the end followed by correspondence and materials concerning the Mark Twain Project. The series concludes with a personal file.
  - Anderson, Frederick -- Correspondence between Baetzhold and Fred Anderson, editor of the Mark Twain Papers, discussing Baetzhold's contributions, 1968 - 1974
  - Baender, Paul -- Correspondence between Baetzhold and Paul Baender of the University of Iowa, 1964 - 1968
  - Baskin, Marsden, Sharlow: Elmira -- Correspondence with Elmira College staff, 1977 - 2004
  - Branch, Edward -- Correspondence, 1965 - 1992
  - Boyer, John Vincent: Mark Twain Memorial (MTM) -- Letters to Baetzhold thanking him for his membership, 1990
  - Budd, Louis -- Correspondence, 1960 - 2002
  - Doyno, Victor -- Correspondence, 1990 - 1992
  - Emerson, Everett -- Correspondence, 1987 - 1997
  - Gerber, John -- Correspondence, 1964 - 1967
  - Gribben, Alan -- Correspondence and photocopied articles, 1976 - 1991
  - Gwiasda, Karl -- Correspondence, 1969 - 1991
  - Kruse, Horst -- Correspondence, 1989 - 1999
  - Kiskis, Michael -- Correspondence and two Kiskis articles, 1988 - 1990
  - Hoffman, Andrew: "Inventing Mart Twain" -- Correspondence, notes, letter of recommendation and review, 1994 - 2001
  - Quirk, Thomas -- Correspondence, 1993 - 2004
  - Rogers, Frank -- Correspondence, 1987
  - Tenney, Tom -- Correspondence, includes Tenney's, "Mark Twain: A Documentary Life", 1980 - 2005
  - Tuckey, John -- Correspondence and article on Tuckey, 1979 - 1984
  - Miscellaneous Twain Correspondence, 1952 - 2005
  - Mark Twain Project (1) -- Collection of materials on Robert Hirst and the Mark Twain Papers at University of California at Berkeley, 1987 - 1992
  - Mark Twain Project (2) -- Includes correspondence, NEH application, reports and Final Performance Report, 1980 - 1992
  - Mark Twain Project (3) -- NEH application (1986, 1990), correspondence and photocopied articles from 1992, 1986 - 1992
  - Mark Twain Project (4) -- "The Mark Twain Project's Correspondence with Messrs. Alan Gribben, Hamlin L. Hill, Everett Emerson, and others (1984-1985)" (bound) RESTRICTED UNTIL 2035
  - Mark Twain Project: Editions -- Correspondence, information on NEH grant application (1987), 1972 - 1987
  - Personal File: Curriculum Vitae, photographs, obit., 1998